Boyd, Ralph F.; Papers apap165
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers1943-1992
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Boyd, Ralph Fredric
apap165
1.6 cubic ft.
The Ralph Boyd, Sr. Papers contain personal and professional correspondence, news clippings, work manuals and agendas that document his career as a General Electric employee, community activist and member of the Schenectady branch of the NAACP.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted with the exception of a small number of folders noted on the inventory below.
Acquisition Information
Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. donated his papers to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections in 1993.
Biographical Sketch
Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. is a lifelong social justice advocate well known for his commitment to civil rights, equality, civil service and local community activism within Schenectady, New York. Born in 1919 in Norfolk, V.A, and raised in Baltimore M.D, Boyd grew up in the segregated south during a time when discrimination and racism plagued many northern and southern communities. Although there were occasional hardships, the support and importance of family, along with the community of church, acted as Boyd’s savior. He credits both components for instilling strong moral values within him.
Upon graduating from Frederick Douglass High School, Boyd continued his education by attending Morgan College, now Morgan State University, in Baltimore. He was able to complete two years before World War II disrupted his college life. While serving in the U.S. Army, he was part of the all black (segregated) 366 Infantry Regiment that would later go on to be recognized and honored for its performance during the war.
Despite the fact that Boyd, and many other African-Americans, were willing to fight in the war for the cause of democracy and protection of their country, the reception these skilled veterans received upon returning home was not a welcoming one. Boyd returned home, realized that nothing had changed and was concerned.
Discontented with the status quo of society, following the war efforts abroad, Boyd decided that he would work to effect change. His first target would be the General Electric Co., a company which previously denied him employment when he first inquired about a job soon after the war. Boyd was told that he didn’t have the training to fulfill a position within the company in spite of his skilled experience in the U.S. Army. General Electric eventually began to hire African-Americans in 1948, including Boyd, but this would not be the end of the trouble that Boyd would endure, nor would it be the end of other problems that he noticed. Not only were African-Americans being treated unfairly, women were being treated unequally as well. Boyd began to defend his female co-workers who were not being paid the same as the men. Despite the obstacles placed forth, Boyd remained within General Electric. He would eventually become a prominent spokesperson and leader for the International Union of Electronic, Electrical, Salaried, Machine and Furniture Workers (IUE) Local 301 union as well as the foreman in the Turbine-Generator Department. He continued working for General Electric for 34 years, up until his retirement in 1982.
In addition to campaigning for change within General Electric, Ralph Boyd also worked within the local community of Schenectady to advocate change for the social, political and economic conditions for African-Americans. Noted for his local community activism, he was elected as a delegate to the Democratic National Convention in 1968. Possessing both the passion and eagerness to see everybody within society treated equally, alongside his interest in community activities, Boyd, in company with friends and colleagues, established and developed the Schenectady chapter of the NAACP in 1950. Serving as the chapter’s president for several terms, in addition to undertaking the responsibility of each post within the organization during his years of involvement, Boyd promoted and supported initiatives for reform change in areas surrounding the housing “slums” within Schenectady. These initiatives include, but were not limited to, acquiring affordable housing for low income groups and improving the conditions within the slums to make the surroundings acceptable for proper living. In addition to his focus on housing, Boyd also campaigned for equality within education and was instrumental in the establishment of the Baptist Retirement Center in 1977. The Baptist Retirement Center, which is located in Scotia, New York, provides activities and medical care for seniors and is the result of Boyd’s desire to see a nursing home within the local community that would facilitate care for those elderly in need.
As a social justice advocate, Ralph Boyd’s work within the Schenectady community is both acknowledged and highly praised. He has won numerous awards, one which identified him as a Schenectady Patroon in 2008, an award that is the city’s equivalent to the Nobel Prize. General Electric named him a winner of the Gerald L. Phillippe Award for Distinguished Public Service in 1978.
The information provided above was gleaned from the following sources, in addition to those found in the Ralph F. Boyd Sr. Papers themselves:
Scope and Contents
The Ralph Boyd, Sr. Papers document his social activism as member of the Schenectady branch of the NAACP and his professional work as an employee of the General Electric Co. in Schenectady, New York. The collection is comprised of General Electric manuals and Boyd’s personal work papers created during his time as a foreman in addition to news clippings and supplementary materials from the International Union of Electronic, Electrical, Salaried, Machine and Furniture Workers (IUE) Local 301. Furthermore, the collection contains materials and news clippings related to his work with the Schenectady branch of the NAACP, initiatives for low-income housing reform, and personal and professional correspondence.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized alphabetically. There are no series.
African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Schenectady, New York; Labor; Social action--New York (State); Community organization--New York (State); Race relations; Labor unions--New York (State); Slums--New York (State); Women--Employment; African Americans--Employment; Segregation in education; Schenectady (N.Y.); Clippings; Correspondence; Files by subject; Bylaws (administrative records); Appointment books; Calendars; Manuals (instructional manuals); Brochures; Minutes; Speeches; Newsletters; Programs; Boyd, Ralph Fredric; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Schenectady Branch; General Electric Company; International Union of Electronic, Electrical, Salaried, Machine and Furniture Workers
- Acknowledged Life Members of NAACP, 1965; 1970 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 1)
- AFL-CIO Central Labor Council Constitution and By-Laws, Undated (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 2)
- Boyd's Appointment Calendar, 1971 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 3)
- Boyd's Personnel File - [RESTRICTED], 1979 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 4)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Must consult archivist before viewing this material.
- Boyd's Work Documents, 1980; Undated (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 5)
- Census Awareness and Instructions, 1980 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 6)
- Dr. Martin Luther King Day Program, 1983 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 7)
- Electric City #259 I.B.P.O.E of W, 1977 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 8)
- Electrical Union News, 1949 February 25-1950 April 14; 1952 February 08-1954 June 17 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 9)
- Employee Disciplinary Letters (memos)- [RESTRICTED], 1978-1980; Undated (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 10)
- Fiscal Calendar, 1980 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 11)
- Forman's Schedule, 1978-1980 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 12)
- G.E-I.U.E Pension and Insurance Agreement/Local Supplemental Agreement, 1955-1956; 1973 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 13)
- General Correspondence (General Electric), 1977-1978; 1980-1981 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 14)
- General Electric Employee Benefits, 1979 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 15-16)
- General Electric- Employee Relations Survey, 1981 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 17)
- General Electric- Forman's Working Handbook - Folder 19 [RESTRICTED], 1975-1976 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 18-19)
- General Electric- Highlights History 1878-1978 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 20)
- General Electric- Production and Inventory Control Manual, 1981 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 21-22)
- General Electric Retirees- Pension Fund-Retirement Plans, 1992; Undated (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 23)
- General Electric- Shop Operations Manual, 1977; 1979-1980 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 24-25)
- General Electric Small Polish Methods and Changes, 1977; 1979-1981 (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 26-27)
- Helen Quirini- Personal/Professional Correspondence- Newsletter Clippings, 1943-1980; Undated (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 28)
- Housing: Schenectady Slums, Shortage, Reform, Business, 1965; 1967-1975; Undated (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 29-32)
- Housing-Slums-Architecture-Real Tax, 1959-1960; 1966-1968; 1970; Undated (Box 1 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 33)
- Human Rights- Schenectady County- New York State Division, 1981; Undated (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 1)
- Integrated/Segregated Education, 1968; 1970; 1972; Undated (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 2)
- IUE-CIO News, 1951 September 13 (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 3)
- Local 301 Annual Report and Directory, 1944 (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 4)
- Local 301 News, 1956 October 19-1956 November 30; 1967 May 05-1967 October 13; 1969 February 18-1980 May 13 (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 5)
- Local 301- Union Election, 1980 (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 6)
- NAACP Annual Convention, 1964; 1969-1970 (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 7)
- NAACP Backgrounders (unemployment/social welfare), 1967; Undated (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 8)
- NAACP Church Social Action Survey, Undated (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 9)
- NAACP Committees including Schenectady Executive Committee Members, 1967; Undated (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 10)
- NAACP Constitution and By-Laws for Branches, 1978 (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 11)
- NAACP "Heroes of Emancipation", 1964 (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 12)
- NAACP Human Rights Unity Ball, 1971 (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 13)
- NAACP-Internal Branch Voting /Office Holding, 1970 (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 14)
- NAACP Labor Manual, 1968 (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 15)
- NAACP Membership Campaign, Undated (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 16)
- NAACP Military Veteran Affairs (newsletter), 1971 (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 17)
- NAACP Newsletters (Schenectady and Albany Chapters), 1967; 1970 (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 18)
- NAACP- N.Y State and Local Voting/Representation, 1970 (Box 2 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 19)
- NAACP Pamphlets/Brochures, 1963; 1968-1970; Undated (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 1)
- NAACP Public Relations-Media Coverage-Political Action, Undated (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 2)
- NAACP Resolutions, Undated (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 3)
- NAACP Schenectady Branch Financial Statement, 1982 (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 4)
- NAACP Schenectady Branch Letterhead/Branch President R. Boyd Response Letter, 1967; Undated (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 5)
- National Committee Against Discrimination in Housing (NCDH) "Trends In Housing" Newsletter, 1981 (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 6)
- National NAACP Housing Department Committee, 1968-1969; Undated (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 7)
- New York State Conference of NAACP Branches, 1982 (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 8)
- Phillippe Award (newsletters), 1978 (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 9)
- Power of Women- General Electric Union, Undated (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 10)
- Schenectady Branch NAACP President's Death- Boyd's Personal Notes/Obituary, 1971; Undated (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 11)
- Schenectady City Planning Commission (newsletters), 1967 (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 12)
- Schenectady NAACP Event and Service Programs/Agendas-, 1971; 1975; 1981-1982 (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 13)
- Turbine Department/Schenectady Utilities Union Relations Advices, 1969; Undated (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 14)
- U.E 201 News, 1953 October 29-1953 December 09 (Box 3 (Ralph F. Boyd, Sr. Papers ), Folder 15)